Guide to the Martin Shubik Papers, 1947-2009 and undated, bulk 1960-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Martin Shubik papers 1947-2009 and undated bulk 1960-2009
Shubik, Martin.
45 linear feet
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Professor Emeritus of Economics, Seymour H. Knox Professor of Mathematical Institutional Economics, Yale University The Martin Shubik Papers span the years 1947 through 2009, and are organized into the following series: Audiovisual Materials, Class Notes, Conferences and Seminars, Correspondence, Personal Files, Professional Service, Teaching Materials, and the largest series, Writings and Research. The materials document Shubik's career as an academic economist, a career most noted for his contributions to game theory and related mathematical studies, but also for his analyses of behavior and risk, corporate competition, defense and war game analysis, nuclear deterrence, economic equilibrium, financial institutions, prices, interest, and bankruptcy. His collaborations with fellow economists and mathematicians, among whom Arrow, Debreu, Friedman, Mas-Colell, Morgenstern, Nash, Samuelson, Shapley, and Weinberg, are documented in the many boxes of correspondence and in research and conference files containing comments, notes, and additional correspondence.
shubik
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Martin Shubik were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift and as deposits from 1992 to 2008.
Biographical Note
1926 Mar. 24 Martin Shubik born in New York, N.Y.
1947 Received B.A. in Mathematics, University of Toronto
1949 M.A., Mathematics, University of Toronto
1951 M.A., Economics, Princeton University
1953 Awarded Ph.D. in Economics, Princeton University
1953-1955 Research Associate, Princeton University
1955-1956 Fellow, Center for Advanced Study, Palo Alto, Ca.
1956-1960 Consultant, General Electric Company
1957-1959 Adjunct Research Professor, Pennsylvania State University
1959 Publication of Strategy and Market Structure
1961-1963 Staff Member, T. J. Watson Research Labs., IBM
1963- Professor of Economics, Seymour H. Knox Professor of Mathematical Institutional Economics, Yale University
1970-1971 Consultant, RAND Corporation
1971 Fellow, Econometric Society
1973-1976 Director, Cowles Foundation, Yale University
1975 Fellow, World Academy of Arts and Sciences
1982 Publication of Game Theory in the Social Sciences
1985 Fellow, American Academy of Arts and Sciences
1999-2010 Publication of The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, Vols. 1-3
2001 With Paul Bracken, published article titled War Gaming in the Information Age: Theory and Purpose, in the Naval War College Review
2010 Recognized by the American Economic Association as a Distinguished Fellow for his contributions to the field
Collection Overview
The Martin Shubik Papers span the years 1947 through 2009, with the bulk of the material ranging from the 1960s to 2009, and are organized into the following series: Audiovisual Materials, Class Notes, Conferences and Seminars, Correspondence, Personal Files, Professional Service, Teaching Materials, and the largest series, Writings and Research. The materials document Shubik's career as an academic economist, a career most noted for his contributions to game theory and related mathematical studies, but also for his analyses of behavior and risk, corporate competition, defense and war game analysis, nuclear deterrence, economic equilibrium, financial institutions, prices, interest, and bankruptcy.
The bulk of the collection consists of typed drafts and reprints of most of Shubik's scholarly publications, and extensive files of professional correspondence, but there are also Shubik's notes as a student, his own course materials such as syllabi and lectures, files on his role as conference organizer and participant, records of his consultancy work with the RAND Corporation, the Yale University Cowles Foundation for Economic Research, and personal files containing biographical information, reviews, reminiscences, a poem, and a few pieces of personal correspondence. His collaborations with fellow economists and mathematicians, among whom Arrow, Debreu, Friedman, Mas-Colell, Morgenstern, Nash, Samuelson, Shapley, and Weinberg, are documented in the many boxes of correspondence and in research and conference files containing comments, notes, and additional correspondence.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Arrow, Kenneth, 1921-; Debreu, Gerard; Friedman, Milton, 1912-2006; Mas-Colell, Andreu; Morgenstern, Oskar, 1902-; Nash, John F., 1928-; Samuelson, Paul A. (Paul Anthony), 1915-2009.; Shapley, Lloyd S., 1923-; Shubik, Martin; Rand Corporation; Weinberg, Alvin Martin, 1915-; Yale University. Cowles Foundation for Research in Economics; Bankruptcy -- Economic aspects; Deterrence (Strategy); Economics, Mathematical; Economics -- Computer simulation; Economics -- Study and teaching; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Equilibrium (Economics); Financial institutions -- Economic aspects; Game theory; Game theory -- Congresses; Interest; Prices; War -- Mathematical models; Audio tapes
Description of Collection
- Audiovisual Materials Series, 1965, 1971 and undated, (1 box)
  Contains fifteen audio tapes on reels varying in size from 8" to 3", chiefly lectures given by Shubik. Drafts of many of these lectures may be found in the Writings and Research Series. Titles are taken from original labels and notes on containers. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Book review, undated (Box 1)
  - Contents: first day AM, Dr. Shubik!
  - Gaming, lecture, 1965 [TRT: 00:32:00]
  - Gaming conference, tape 2, records, two sides, 15/16, 1971
  - Gaming conference, tape 3, one side, 15/16, 1971 (architectural sketch on cover)
  - Game theory, Shubik lecture, no. 1, 3/9
  - Game theory, Shubik lecture, no. 2, 2/16
  - Tape 1, chapter 5 [and Firestone?], undated
  - Tape from Shubik (at RAND), addressed to Mrs. E. Walker, Yale, 7/23
  - Transcribe for Prof. Deutsch, tape no. 2, Shubik lecture, undated
  - Transcribe for Prof. Deutsch, tape no. 3, Shubik lecture, undated
  - Unidentified tape 3, undated
  - Unidentified tape 6, undated
  - Unidentified tape 7, undated
  - Unidentified tape, undated
- Class Notes Series, 1947-1954 and undated, bulk 1949-1950, (1 box)
  Contains written notes, examinations, assignments and reading lists of classes that Shubik attended during his studies at the University of Toronto and Princeton University. Also contains detailed notes taken by Shubik on courses given by prominent economists such as his thesis advisor Oskar Morgenstern, Jacob Viner, Henry Wallich and Friedrich A. Lutz during Shubik's time at Princeton University. Shubik noted his teachers' position on topics, such as Morgenstern's views on forecasting in economics. Also includes notes taken by Shubik relating to books he was reading, with summaries of chapters and detailed comments that include his own position on the texts. Arranged chronologically.
  - Exams at the University of Toronto and Princeton University, 1947-1950 (Box 2)
  - International Economics, Fall 1948-Spring 1949
  - Unsolved Problems in Mathematical Economics, 1949
  - Business Cycles with Oskar Morgenstern, 1949
  - Mathematics, 1949
  - International Trade with Jacob Viner, Fall 1949 and Fall 1950
  - Economic Theory with F. Lutz, Fall 1949 and Spring 1950
  - Statistics, Fall 1949
  - Money with Henry Wallich, Spring 1950
  - Statistics, 1954
  - Cycle Theory, undated
  - Princeton fourth year reading list, undated
- Conferences and Seminars Series, 1957-2008 and undated, (6 boxes)
  Contains notes and transcripts on lectures and talks, trip reports, conference announcements and proposals, correspondence around the organization of workshops. Files from earlier years include participation lists, notes, drafts of papers Shubik or others presented and programmes of workshops and symposia that reflect Shubik's professional engagements outside the university, such as his consultancy activities for General Electric Company, the Office of Naval Research, and RAND. Files of later years contain materials from workshops on game theory, gaming, symposia and lectures about and in celebration of Oskar Morgenstern, as well as luncheon seminar talks at Yale University. Arranged chronologically.
  - Economics and Operations Research, 1957 (Box 2)
  - The Third Conference on Games, 1959
  - Orientation Seminar Manufacturing Systems Simulation, 1959
  - Conference on Simulations of a Business, 1959
  - TIMS-IST Conference on Adaptive Systems, 1960
  - Third International Conference on Operational Research, 1963
  - Mathematical-Arms Control and Disarmament Agency Conference, 1966
  - Conference on the Future Impact of Computers, 1966
  - Scientific Decision Making for Tomorrow's Marketing, London, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Stenographic Transcript of Proceedings of the Westinghouse Marketing Seminar, 1966
  - Conference on Research and Technology, Office of Naval Research, 1968
  - Latin America Symposium, 1970
  - Conference on Politics of Corporate Planning and Modeling, 1970
  - Proposal for Conference on The Purposes, Goals and Validation Procedures for Military Gaming, 1970
  - Conference on Models, Simulations and Games, 1973
  - Symposium on Global Modeling, Bader, 1974
  - Conference on The Micro-economic Foundation of Macro-economics, Spain, April 21-26, 1975
  - Agenda of America Conference, 1975
  - Fire Support Methodology Workshop, August 4-7, 1975
  - Workshop on Economic Conflict and National Security Research, 1976
  - Fourth International Workshop on Game Theory, June 1978
  - Workshop on Gaming as an Aid in Policy Formulation and Implementation, August 29-September 1, 1978
  - Conference on Mathematical Models of Conflict and Combat: Uses and Theory, November 1-3, 1979
  - Conference Auctions and Biddings: Uses and Theory, December 6-8, 1979
  - Conferences, 1975-1979
  - Gaming Conference, 1971-1974
    - Conference notes and memos (Box 4)
    - Conference participant information
    - Conference first day
    - Conference write-ups
    - Transcripts, (2 folders)
    - Conference questionnaire
    - Status of gaming conference proceedings, 1972-1974
  - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, Talk in Vienna, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Oskar Morgenstern Symposium on Mathematical Economics & Econometrics, 1980
  - Oskar Morgenstern Vorlesung, 1980
  - Symposium Taking Decisions: Can Information Technology Help?, 1980
  - Conferences, 1980
  - Conference on Managing International Risk, 1981
  - Conferences, 1983
  - The Interest Rate Dilemma, 1983
  - RAND Conference, 1983
  - Talk on Strategic Marketing and Minimal Financial Institutions, 1984
  - Conferences, 1984
  - Conferences on Takeovers and Contests for Corporate Control, 1985
  - Conferences, 1985
  - Conference on Peace, Defense and Economic Analysis, 1985
  - Conferences, 1960-1985
  - Talk on What is an Application and When is Theory a Waste of Time?, New Orleans, 1987
  - Conferences, 1988
  - Conference Defense and Deterrence: Economics, History and Political Science Approaches, 1988
  - Siena Workshop, 1988
  - NBER Conference Economics of Art Museums, 1989
  - Distinguished Lecture Series at The University of Southern California, 1989
  - Talk Risk, Society, Politicians, Scientists and People, May 22, 1989
  - Conferences, 1983-1990
  - Lectures given, 1988-1991
  - Conferences and Invitations, 1989-1991
  - Siena Conference Economic Notes, November 22-25, 1990
  - Conferences, 1989-1990 (Box 6)
  - Conference on The History of Game Theory, 1990
  - University of Maryland (McGuire) Lecture, April 3-4, 1990
  - Decision Sciences Colloquium, Gus Stuart, Harvard University, 1991-1992
  - Conference on Learning, Rationality and Games, 1991
  - Wesleyan University Seminar, 1991
  - Symposium on Just Winners and Losers: The Application of Game Theory to Corporate Law and Practice, 1991
  - Conferences, 1991
  - Symposium on Game Theory, University of Cincinnati, 1991
  - Economic Notes Conference, Siena, 1992
  - Biology and Economics Conference, 1992
  - Conference The Future of the World's Financial Institutions, 1992
  - Monte dei Paschi di Siena Conference, November 18-19, 1992
  - Seminar on The American Market for the Visual Arts and High Quality Crafts, 1993
  - Hong Kong, 1993
  - Economic Theory and Future: Economics, Physics, and Biology, Santa Fe, 1993
  - Draft for Wilton Park Presentation, Utgott, Victor A., September 24-26, 1993
  - International Security Program Luncheon Seminars, 1993
  - Stony Brook, July 30, 1993
  - Morgenstern, Oskar, Vienna, 1993
  - Minister des Affaires Internationales Seminar, Quebec, March 17, 1993
  - Conference The Global Economy as a Complex Adaptive System, Santa Fe, September 7-15, 1993
  - Siena and Copenhagen, November 18-29, 1993
  - Conference on Biology, Information and the Future of National Security, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Conference on Coping with Financial Instability, 1994
  - Conferences, 1992-1995
  - Mackintosh Lecture, Queens University, October 6-7, 1994
  - Biology, Information and the RMA Conference, Andrew Marshall, Virginia, July 12-13, 1994
  - 50th Anniversary of The Theory of Games and Economic Behavior, Barcelona, 1994
  - Triangle Universities Security Seminar, University of North Carolina, September 14, 1994
  - Incontri di Rocca Salimbeni, Siena, November 25, 1994
  - Conferences on Naval Technology, December 18-20, 1995
  - Conference The Information Revolution and International Security, May 8-10, 1996
  - Siena Conference Risks Involving Derivatives and Other New Financial Instruments, 1996
  - NBER Conference on General Equilibrium and Economic Theory, May 3-4, 1997
  - Conference on Themes in Economics, Celebration of I. Fisher, May 1998
  - Barcelona Conference on Museums, 1998
  - Financial Expert Conference, 1999
  - Seminar, Participation of Mandelbrot, 1999
  - Cowles Foundation Lunch Seminar, Money, 2000
  - Conference, Missing Financial Markets, April 27, 2001
  - Conference, Incomplete Markets and Strategic Market Games, April 28-29, 2001
  - Conference, New Horizons in Search Theory: From Abstraction to Application, May 21-23, 2001
  - Talk, Can a Central Bank's Interest Rate Policy Control Inflation?, 2001
  - Talk, A Survey of Strategic Market Games, Stony Brook, 2001
  - Lecture, inkuBATor wiedzy invitation, Warsaw, 2001
  - Lecture at The Institute of Advanced Study, Vienna, 2001
  - Talks/Presentations by Shubik, 2001-2002
  - Talk, July 27, 2003
  - Seminar, Mathematical Institutional Economics, Santa Fe, 2006
  - Economics Seminar, UNM Economics Department on A Game-Theoretic Approach to the Theory of Money, March 31, 2006
  - Computational Philosophy Lessons from Simple Models, 2007
  - It's Not Just a Game, Sept. 2, 2008
  - Yale University Workshop on Environment and Security, Invitation List, undated
  - Talk, undated
  - Talk, Game Theory and Operations Research, undated
  - Cowles Lunch Talk, "Reminiscences" of Shubik, undated
  - Colloquium series, Santa Fe Institute, Three Lectures on The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, undated
  - Game Theory Workshop trip report, undated
  - Talk, Time and Money, undated
  - International Security Studies and Arms Control-Defense Policy Seminar, Yale University, undated
  - List of participants, undated
  - List of assumptions by one panel member, undated
- Correspondence Series, 1955-2007, (38 boxes)
  The series is divided into two subseries as originally organized by Shubik: by year, and alphabetically by last name. The alphabetical sequence also includes an initial folder for each letter, with single pieces of correspondence. The correspondence includes comments on the work of other economists, debates on current issues, recommendation letters, referee reports, submissions, discussions with book editors, and attachments. Among his most frequent correspondents is his longtime collaborator Lloyd S. Shapley, as well as other major twentieth-century economists such as Oskar Morgenstern, John Nash, Kenneth Arrow, Gerard Debreu, Paul Samuelson, Milton Friedman and Andreu Mas-Colell. There are several cards and pieces of humorous intent that are most likely from Nash.
  There are substantial folders of correspondence relating to Shubik's major works and the publication process; other exchanges related to his writings can be found in the Writings and Research Series. Other correspondence reflects Shubik's engagement with Yale University through most of his professional life, as well as his work as a staff member at IBM, as visiting professor at Universidade de Chile, as consultant at the RAND Corporation, and as director of the Cowles Foundation for Research in Economics. The series also contains Shubik's non-academic correspondence with newspapers, magazines, companies and museums. Note: Additional correspondence can be found throughout the other series in the collection.
  - Correspondence by Date, "1694"-2009
    - "1694"-1958 (Box 8)
    - 1960, (3 folders)
    - 1961, (1-3 of 4 folders)
    - 1961, (4 of 4 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1962, (2 folders)
    - 1963, (1 of 2 folders)
    - 1963, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1964, (4 folders
    - 1965, (1 of 3 folders)
    - 1965, (2-3 of 3 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1966, (4 folders)
    - 1967, (5 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1968, (1 of 5 folders)
    - 1968, (2-5 of 5 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1969, (1-2 of 5 folders)
    - 1969, (3-5 of 5 folders) (Box 14)
    - 1970, (1-3 of 4 folders)
    - 1970, (4 of 4 folders) (Box 15)
    - 1971, (3 folders)
    - 1972, (1 of 2 folders)
    - 1972, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 16)
    - 1973, (4 folders)
    - 1974, (4 folders) (Box 17)
    - 1975, (1 of 4 folders)
    - 1975, (2-4 of 4 folders) (Box 18)
    - 1976, (1-2 of 3 folders)
    - 1976, (3 of 3 folders) (Box 19)
    - 1977, (4 folders)
    - 1978, (3 folders) (Box 20)
    - 1979, (3 folders)
    - 1980, (3 folders) (Box 21)
    - 1981, (2 folders)
    - 1982, (2 folders) (Box 22)
    - 1983, (1-2 of 5 folders)
    - 1983, (3-5 of 5 folders) (Box 23)
    - 1984, (2 folders)
    - 1985, (5 folders) (Box 24)
    - 1986, (4 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1987, (1 of 4 folders)
    - 1987, (2-4 of 4 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1988, (1 of 2 folders)
    - 1988, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 27)
    - 1989, (4 folders)
    - 1990, (4 folders) (Box 28)
    - 1991, (3 folders) (Box 29)
    - 1992, (1 of 4 folders)
    - 1992, (2-4 of 4 folders) (Box 30)
    - 1993, (2 folders)
    - 1994, (2 folders) (Box 31)
    - 1995, (2 folders)
    - 1996, (2 folders) (Box 32)
    - 1997, (2 folders)
    - 1998, (1 of 2 folders)
    - 1998, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 33)
    - 1999, (1-3 of 5 folders)
    - 1999, (4-5 of 5 folders) (Box 34)
    - 2000, (4 folders)
    - 2001, (4 folders) (Box 35)
    - 2002, (2 folders)
    - 2003, (1 folder) (Box 36)
    - 2004-2009, (1 folder)
  - Alphabetical Correspondence Subseries, 1961-2005
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1980s-1990s (Box 36)
    - Advisory Commission of the Division of the Social Sciences, 1980s
    - Aequus Institute, grants, 1990s
    - Alfred Sloan Foundation, 1997
    - American Economic Review, 1960s-1980s
    - Barry O'Neill, 1996
    - Book permission requests for Market Structure and Behavior, 1979
    - Book, The War Game, 1979-1980
    - Brainware, 1990s
    - Brazil, 1971-1974
    - Bracken, Jerome, 1991
    - Canada Council, 1974-1983
    - Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1994
    - Center for Competitive and Conflict Systems Research, 1980s
    - Central Intelligence Agency, 1965-1979
    - ARPA-related correspondence, 1970s (Box 37)
    - Chile, 1965
    - China, 1993-1994
    - Commission on the Year 2000, Computer Committee, 1967-1972
    - Conferences, 1970s
    - Conflict Conference, 1979
    - Correspondence on Conference on Evaluation of Art of Gaming, RAND, 1971
    - Cowles Commission budget, 1967-1975
    - "D" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s-1990s
    - Decision Models of Strategic Conflict, 1981
    - Economic notes, Siena, 1997
    - Econophysics, 2005
    - Letters to editors, etc., 1974
    - "F" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s
    - Fan mail, 1992 and 1994
    - Finance recruiting, 1970s
    - Ford Foundation, 1986-1990
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences and Game Theory in Economics, 1966-1992
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, 1980s, (1 of 3 folders)
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, 1980s, (2-3 of 3 folders) (Box 38)
    - Games for Society, Business and War, 1972-1973
    - Global Alliance for Management Excellence, 1996
    - Handbook of Game Theory with Economic Applications, 1990
    - Harvard University Press, 1970s-1980s
    - Hong Kong, 1994
    - "I" miscellaneous correspondence, 1965-1992
    - Institute for Advanced Studies, 1970-1983
    - International Journal of Game Theory, 1970s
    - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, 1977-1984
    - "J" miscellaneous correspondence, 1977-1988
    - Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, California, 1966-1980
    - The Journal of Conflict Resolution, 1960s
    - Journal of Economic Literature, 1970s-1980s
    - Journals, miscellaneous, 1964-1989 (Box 39)
    - Journal of Political Economy, 1972-1980
    - "K" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s
    - Kenya (Ford Foundation), 1972-1973
    - Kluwer Publishers, RISK, 1990s
    - Kumar, 1998
    - "L" miscellaneous correspondence, 1970s-1980s
    - "M" miscellaneous correspondence, 1970s-1990s, (2 folders)
    - M. Shubik festschrift, 1991 (Box 40)
    - Market Structure and Behavior, 1978-1980
    - Mathematics of Conflict, 1980s
    - Morgenstern volume, 1961-1976
    - Museum of Money, 2000
    - "N" miscellaneous correspondence, 1970s-1990s (bulk 1980s)
    - Nash, John, 1990s
    - New York City, 1967
    - New York subway system, 1966-1967
    - Newspapers and magazines, 1990-1991
    - "O" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s
    - Office of Naval Research, 1960s-1980s, (2 folders)
    - Old relevant letters, 1962
    - Operations research, 1967-1968
    - "P" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s-1990s
    - Princeton University Press, 1960s
    - PEW repost, 1989-1990 (Box 41)
    - Proposal evaluation, NSF, 1982-1988
    - "Q" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s-1990s
    - "R" miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s-1990s
    - The RAND Corporation, 1960s-1970s, (1-4 of 5 folders)
    - The RAND Corporation, 1970s, (5 of 5 folders) (Box 40)
    - Recommendation letters, 1970s
    - Recommendation letters, 1977-1978
    - Recommendation letters, 1980-1990
    - Recommendation letters, 1989
    - Recommendation letters, 1990-1991
    - Recommendation letters, forms, 1970-1977
    - Referee file, 1973-1976
    - Referee reports, 1972-1976, (5 folders)
    - Referee reports, 1988-2000, (2 folders) (Box 43)
    - Referee reports by M. Shubik, 1968-1971
    - References, 1974-1978
    - References, bibliographies, 1972-1977
    - Reviews, abstracts, references, 1977-1981
    - Reviews and referees, 1999-2002